healthjobsuk.com 2019-03-30

# Privacy Notice

## Privacy Notice

This privacy notice tells you about how your personal information is handled within our services. We handle personal information for several purposes. For some, purposes we (Trac Systems Ltd) is the data controller. For others, the employer is the data controller. Each is described below.

### Candidate account

Some personally identifiable information will be managed for your candidate account. The information is needed to provide the account through which job applications are made and managed, keep you informed about the service and to operate the opt-in Jobs-by-Email service. The lawfulness of processing is established under the General Data Protection Regulation article 6(1)(a) by your consent. Where you have a job application in your account, consent lawfulness of processing is also established under GDPR article 6(1)(b).

Your candidate account has a small number of fields about you, such as your contact details. They are held on the account so that you can change your details in one place and have them automatically applied to all applications in progress - for example if you change your address.

Your candidate account also has your communications preferences and those for the Jobs-by-Email service to notify you about job vacancies if you choose to enable that feature. 

You can edit your details preferences by logging into your candidate account.

If you do not provide information as needed this may prevent the account from being established or operated, and therefore prevent you from being able to make or manage your job application.

If you decide that you wish to erase your candidate account, you can login and do so. If there are job applications connected to the account then it will instead be placed into hibernation until they have expired and the account will then be erased automatically.

Your account will also be erased automatically if you have not logged in for 730 days, are not subscribed to Jobs-by-Email, have no job applications and are not part of a redeployment exercise or talent pool.

The data controller for this information is Trac Systems Ltd (www.trac.systems). Trac Systems provide an application tracking system, some recruitment support services and have staff and secure data storage located entirely in the UK.

You may contact [dataprotection@trac.systems](mailto:dataprotection@trac.systems) if you need to make an enquiry, a request for your personal information held as part of this candidate account, or to arrange for any mistakes to be corrected. If you have a complaint, please contact us so that we can investigate.

The privacy notice pertaining to your candidate account is displayed on the login and account registration pages.

### From job application to starting work

Personally identifiable information will be managed from the job application through to starting work. The information is needed to help recruit the best people, perform the necessary employment checks, arrange a contract of employment, get new recruits started in their work and fulfil legal/regulatory requirements. These are necessary steps prior to being able to establish, continue or vary a contract of employment.

In some special cases your information may have been entered without your having completed a job application. For example, where students are being placed from a training provider (and your information has been received from that training provider) or where employment checks need to be carried out on existing staff.

During recruitment, the recruiters consider the information provided on the job application form and that provided for assessments and interviews.

As you get further through the process, employment checks may need to be performed such as identity, right-to-work (immigration), criminal records, professional registration, qualifications, references, occupational health and other checks. More information or documentation, such as proof of identity documents, may be needed from you. Only the necessary information is shared with organisations where they assist us with these checks and it is only for the purpose of performing those checks.

To get a new recruit started in their work, induction training and some administrative requirements are completed. Some information will be requested from you at that time, such as bank details for your salary payments and emergency contact details in case you have an emergency at work. The information for those who have been recruited is entered into the employee management and records keeping systems that are used by the employer.

If you do not provide information as needed, this may hinder or prevent your application or employment.

Any information you provide about your ethnic origin, religious beliefs and sexual orientation is used only for equal opportunities statistical monitoring of the recruitment process and workforce. It is protected throughout the process, is not visible to those assessing your application or to hiring managers, and cannot be used in a way which can identify you. It will not affect your application if you choose to not provide this information.

If you indicate that you can be considered for a preferential or guaranteed interview owing to a disability you have, that information is used only for the purposes of arranging interviews.

If you decide that you wish to leave a job application process, you can login to your applicant account then withdraw your application. For special cases (examples above) you should instead contact the employer.

Your information about your application through to starting work is automatically deleted from this recruitment management system once it is no longer regarded as necessary for the purpose for which it was collected. This is 400 days after the date the application was entered in this recruitment system or 200 days after your proposed/actual start date, whichever is the greater. This period allows obligations relating to lawful employment practices to be fulfilled such as statistical reporting and the defending of potential legal claims.

The data controller for this information is the organisation to whom you have applied.

The privacy notice pertaining to a job application is

  * presented prior to starting the application process when applying via your Trac account;
  * sent by email to applicants who details have been added to Trac by the employer; and
  * shown at the end of the stored copy of the application form, visible via your Trac account.

It shows the details for the organisation who is the data controller for your application (usually the employer) and any additional information that they wish to provide to you as part of the notice.

### Disclosure and Barring Service check application form.

This service provides an online Disclosure and Barring Service check application form. The form provides some validation of your answers in order to help minimise the number of forms which are rejected by the Disclosure and Baring Service because they contain errors. When you submit your form, it is stored securely on our system that is dedicated to this purpose. The data controller is Trac Systems Ltd (www.trac.systems).

Once you have completed both your DBS application form and your identity documents have been checked, your DBS application form is checked. If there appear to be problems with your answers then you may be asked to complete the form again. Otherwise it is electronically counter signed and delivered to the DBS via a secure channel.

It is important that you complete the DBS form carefully because it cannot be amended once it has been submitted to the DBS for processing.

Once the DBS have performed their check, this system is notified that result is ready and that either:

  * the certificate contains no disclosure of criminal records information and therefore the employer does not need to see the certificate, or that
  * the certificate does contain a disclosure of criminal records information and therefore the employer should expect you to show your certificate to them.

This system will notify the employer accordingly.

The DBS do not provide this system, Trac Systems Ltd or the employer with information about the contents of a certificate (i.e. not informed of information about criminal records that it may contain).

The DBS certificate is sent by the DBS directly to you as the applicant. It is your responsibility to show your certificate to the employer where required.

If you believe there is a mistake with your certificate, you should appeal this directly with the DBS. They will investigate and reissue the certificate where appropriate.

Completed forms and result information are retained in this system for the time period specified by the DBS for providers who submit electronic checks. After that period they are deleted automatically.

The lawfulness of processing is established under the General Data Protection Regulation article 6(1)(b) as necessary in order to provide you with the service described above and, usually, because it is a necessary step for the contract of employment for which the DBS check is being performed. If you have a complaint, please contact us at [dataprotection@trac.systems](mailto:dataprotection@trac.systems) so that we can investigate.

### Employer's talent pool

This service provides a talent pool feature to employers. The employers add candidates to their talent pool according to their own policies. For example, by collecting sign-ups with consent at a recruitment fair.

Personally identifiable information will be managed for this talent pool record. The information is needed to help operate the talent pool and match candidates to job vacancies. The lawfulness of processing is established because you have given your consent in accordance with General Data Protection Regulation article 6(1)(a) or, in the case of some special talent pools, under GDPR article 6(1)(b) where it is a necessary step prior to being able to establish, continue or vary a contract of employment.

The employer considers candidates who are in the talent pool for job vacancies that arise. When they identify that a candidate may be a match for the vacancy, they send an email message to inform them of the job vacancy and invite them to make an application. Records are kept of communications that are sent and received.

The data controller for this information is the organisation that manages the talent pool. This application tracking system is provided by Trac Systems Ltd (www.trac.systems) as a data processor. Trac Systems provide some recruitment support services and have staff and secure data storage located entirely in the UK.

Your entry in the talent pool expires automatically on a date set when it was added. Your talent pool records in this application tracking system will be automatically deleted after the expiry date. If you decide that you wish to leave before then, please contact the team who manage the talent pool.

To make an enquiry, a request for your personal information held as part of this talent pool, or to arrange for any mistakes to be corrected, you may contact either the team who manage the talent pool or the data controller's Data Protection Officer.

The privacy notice pertaining to a talent pool is sent by email to the candidate at the time of being added to the talent pool. The privacy notice includes the contact details for the organisation who is the data controller for the talent pool (usually the employer).

### Employer's redeployment exercise

From time-to-time, employers undergo restructurings whereby some job roles will cease. Sometimes they make efforts to match those persons whose jobs are at risk with other jobs that become available. Our service allows employers to record the job matching needs of those persons so that they can be matched to those jobs.

Personally identifiable information is needed to help operate the redeployment exercise, match candidates to job vacancies and fulfil legal/regulatory requirements. The lawfulness of processing is established under the General Data Protection Regulation article 6(1)(b) because these are necessary steps prior to being able to establish, continue or vary a contract of employment, or because you have given your consent in accordance with article 6(1)(a).

The employer considers candidates who are in the redeployment pool for job vacancies that arise. When they identify that a candidate may be a match for the vacancy, they send an email message to inform them of the job vacancy and invite them to make an application. Records are kept of communications that are sent and received.

The data controller for this information is the organisation that manages the redeployment exercise. This application tracking system is provided by Trac Systems Ltd (www.trac.systems) as a data processor. Trac Systems provide some recruitment support services and have staff and secure data storage located entirely in the UK.

Your entry in the redeployment pool expires automatically on a date set when it was added. If you decide that you wish to leave before then, please contact the team who are handling your possible redeployment.

Your redeployment records in this application tracking system will be automatically deleted one year after the expiry date. This period is necessary in order to be able to report on success levels of the redeployment exercise and for the possible establishment, exercise or defence of legal claims.

To make an enquiry, a request for your personal information held as part of this redeployment pool, or to arrange for any mistakes to be corrected, you may contact either the team who manage the redeployment pool or the data controller's Data Protection Officer.

The privacy notice pertaining to a redeployment record is sent by email to the candidate at the time of being added to the pool. The privacy notice includes the contact details for the organisation who is the data controller for the redeployment pool (usually the employer).

### Cookies

Web systems are operated by Trac Systems Ltd in order to provide this service. Those web systems set cookies on the browsers of the visitors to the applicable web sites. Those cookies are strictly necessary for running the service and therefore it is not necessary to ask the visitor's consent for the cookies to be set.

No cookies are set by advertisers or tracking companies. No cookies are used for the purposes of building profiles of individuals.
